James A. Pike Papers
James A. Pike Papers
- Writings
  - Sermons
    - "Thou Art the Man!" publ. in Christian Herald, Oct 2, 1960; drafts A and B, printed material; draft C, typescript copy; 3 folders (Box 100)
    - "Frustration: A Fairly Universal Problem" CBS Church of the Air, Sep 24, 1961; printed material (Box 100)
    - "Why Christ?" preached at St. Paul's Episcopal Church, Burlingame, California, Oct 15-17, 1961; printed material (Box 100)
    - "A Department of Religion at U.C.?", Nov 23, 1961; printed material (Box 100)
    - "Cavemen Again?", Dec 3, 1961; draft A, typescript. rev.; draft B, printed material; draft C; printed material; 3 folders (Box 100)
    - [A Children's Sermon], 1962; typescript copy (Box 100)
    - "Church and Race", 1963, May 5; printed material (Box 100)
    - "This Treasure in Earthen Vessels" preached at Christ Church Cathedral, St. Louis, Mo., 1964, Oct 11; drafts A and B, printed material; 2 folders (Box 100)
    - ["You Shall Be As Gods"], preached in New York City(?), 1965(?); typescript (Box 100)
    - [On Luci Johnson's Rebaptism], Jul 4, 1965; typescript (Box 100)
    - "The Meaning of Holy Baptism", Jul 11, 1965; printed material (Box 100)
    - "Signs of Hope" preached at Great St. Mary's, Cambridge, Oct 17, 1965; printed material (Box 100)
    - [On Church's Struggle Against Evil], preached at St. Paul's Church, Blantyre, Malawi, Jan 16, 1966; typescript copy (Box 100)
    - [On What To Believe], Sep 4, 1966; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, printed material; 2 folders (Box 100)
    - "What A Man Can Believe" preached at Unitarian Church, Santa Barbara, California, Sep 11, 1966; printed material (Box 100)
    - "Ecce, quam bonum", Sep 13, 1966; printed material (Box 100)
    - [On Ferment in Church], preached at St. Andrew's Church, Rochester, New York, May 21, 1967; typescript revised (Box 100)
    - "Approaches To Ethics" Art of Living, Jul 2, 1967; typescript repro (Box 100)
    - "Are The Ten Commandments Final?" The Art of Living, Jul 9, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 100)
    - "Are the New Testament Injunctions Absolute?" The Art of Living, Jul 16, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 100)
    - "The Teachings of the Church--Unchanging?" The Art of Living, Jul 23, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 100)
    - "Growth Through Encounter", Jul 28, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 100)
    - "'Natural Law' and Morals" The Art of Living, Jul 30, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 100)
    - "Things and Persons" The Art of Living, Aug 6, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 100)
    - "What Best Serves Persons?" The Art of Living, Aug 13, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 101)
    - "Healing With Love" The Art of Living, Aug 20, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 101)
    - "Judging Yourself and Others" The Art of Living, Aug 27, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 101)
    - "Deciding For Persons" The Art of Living, Sep 3, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 101)
    - "Structure and Conscience" The Art of Living, Sep 10, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 101)
    - "Man For Others" The Art of Living, Sep 17, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 101)
    - "Being Responsible in Context" The Art of Living, Sep 24, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 101)
  - Speeches
    - "An 'Attempt at Prophecy'" Crisis and Opportunity in the Middle East, American Christian Palestine Comm., 1957; published material (Box 101)
    - "The Authority Crisis and Moral Responsibility", 1968; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy revised; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "The Best Things in the Worst Times"
      - Published material, Intercollegian, Mar 1951 (Box 101)
      - Typescript copies, May 14 1952; Oct 25 1955; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "Christianity as Perspective" Partridge Lecture, Middlebury College, Apr 27 1952; typescript copy revised, printed material; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "The Christian's Vocation", typescript copy (Box 101)
    - "The Church and Public Questions" Claremont Men's College, Claremont, California, Mar 22 1962; typescript copy (Box 101)
    - "The Church in an Atomic Age", draft A, typescript copy revised; draft B, typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "Church-Sponsored Education in a Democracy", printed material (Box 101)
    - "The Claim of Situational Ethics", Apr 21 1967; typescript revised reproduction (Box 101)
    - "The Challenge to the Y.M.C.A. as a Christian Organization" Y.M.C.A. 71st State Convention, Apr 1955; printed material (Box 101)
    - "Does the Church Further or Impede the Fulfillment of Democratic Ideals?", typescript revised (Box 101)
    - "The Ethic Beyond Legal Ethics" excerpts, Rosenthal Lectures, Northwestern University Law School, 1962; typescript copy revised (Box 101)
    - "Ecumenism and the Lay Christian", Sep 6, 1964; typescript copy (Box 101)
    - "Ethics of Planned Parenthood", Jan 18 1955; printed material (Box 101)
    - "The Ethics of Family Planning and Social Work Practice", May 26 1959; typescript copy revised (Box 101)
    - "The Future of Religion and Education", printed material (Box 101)
    - "God in A Time of Decision," Yale University, precis of addresses, holograph; printed material; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "Great Wrath--A Short Time", Feb 4, 1966; printed material, published material; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "How To Handle A Sense of Guilt", Feb 8 1953; printed material (Box 101)
    - "Human Suffering", Apr 11 1956; printed material (Box 101)
    - "The Hypocrisy of Modern Morality", Feb 1967; typescript annotated (Box 101)
    - "The Idea of God" Garvin Free Lecture, Apr 4, 1967; typescript copy revised; printed material; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "Inner Security Through Religion", typescript copy; printed material; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "Is the Church Really A Dynamic Force in American Life?" Economic Club, Detroit, Mich., Oct 3, 1960; typescript copy; printed material; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "Is Religion a Vital Force in American Life?" Commonwealth Club of California, May 27 1960; published material (Box 101)
    - "The Issue of Capital Punishment", Mar 1 1960; printed material (Box 101)
    - "Man Himself--Philosophical Aspects" Man in California--1980's, Proceedings of Statewide Conference, Jan 1964; printed material (Box 101)
    - "The Meaning of Christian Vocation" Conference on Christian Responsibility in Economic Decision Making, Washington Cathedral, 1957; printed material (Box 101)
    - "The Meaning of Culture" America-Israel Society, Second National Dinner, Washington, D.C., Apr 26 1955; typescript copy revised, typescript revised (Box 101)
    - "The Meaning of Culture"(?) United Jewish Appeal Dinner, American Jewish Congress, Hotel Pierre, New York City, May 1957; draft A, typescript copy revised; draft B, typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "The Meaning of Life", Jun 8 1960; printed material (Box 101)
    - "Moral Implications of Power and Responsibility", 1956?; typescript revised reproduction (Box 101)
    - "On The Beach", Jan 24 1960; printed material (Box 101)
    - "Parenthood In A Free Nation", Feb 19 1957; typescript copy revised (Box 101)
    - "Planned Parenthood", May 5 1953; typescript copy revised (Box 101)
    - "Prolegomena to Discussion of Church-State Relations", 1953; printed material (Box 101)
    - "The Protestant Dilemma In Education", Jan 29 1953; printed material (Box 101)
    - "The Psychology of Worship" Hadden Memorial Lecture, Feb 28 1952; typescript revised (Box 101)
    - "The Quest Revisited" Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1966; printed material (Box 101)
    - "Religion, Freedom and Conformity" Institute for Religious and Social Studies, Oct 27 1954; published material (Box 101)
    - "The Scope and Price of Prophecy" Interseminary Conference, General Theological Seminary, New York, Oct 26, 1956; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "Sex and Morality: A Confrontation" with Dr. William Banowsky, 20th Century Christian, Mar 1969; published material (Box 101)
    - "The Special Vocation of the Episcopal Church for College Work", Sep 12 1952; printed material (Box 101)
    - "The Sputniks and Our Anxiety", printed material (Box 101)
    - "The Supreme Court Decision On School Prayers", Jul 13, 1964(?); printed material (Box 101)
    - "The Task Ahead", typescript revised (Box 101)
    - "The Task Which the Secularization of the Public School Presents to the Church", May 22, 1951; typescript copy revised; published material; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "The War In Heaven--and on Earth, " Jewish Center, New York, Nov 15, 1955; drafts A and B, typescript copies; 2 folders (Box 101)
    - "Western Morality", May 22 1953; published material (Box 101)
    - Untitled
      - On anti-Catholic hate movement and Roman Catholic candidate, Michigan State Fair, Detroit, Mich., Sep 4 1960; typescript copy (Box 101)
      - On the approach used to interest people in Christianity, incomplete, typescript (Box 101)
      - On Breakdown of Western Civilization, 100th Anniversary of Y.M.C.A., typescript copy (Box 101)
      - On Christianity and Freedom, 111th Convention, Diocese of California, Jan 31 1961; printed material (Box 101)
      - On Decline of Church as Challenge, 115th Convention, Diocese of California, Feb 1 1965; printed material (Box 101)
      - On developing social consciousness in lawyers, incomplete, typescript (Box 101)
      - On Episcopacy, typescript revised (Box 102)
      - On Ethics of Legal Profession, Legal Aid Society, published material (Box 102)
      - On first amendment, Commonwealth Club of California, Jul 13 1962; published material (Box 102)
      - On frustration, Fourth Lecture, Adult Conference, Drew University, Madison, N.J., Jun 19 1952; typescript revised (Box 102)
      - On inhibition, Fifth Lecture, Adult Conference, Drew University, Madison, N.J., Jun 20 1952; typescript revised (Box 102)
      - On Israel, Assembly on Middle East, San Francisco, California, Feb 1964; typescript revised (Box 102)
      - On Legal Ethics, American Bar Association, Legal Education Section, Aug 17, 1954; typescript copy; excerpts, typescript copy; 2 folders (Box 102)
      - On Legalizing Abortion, Conference of Barristers, State Bar Convention, Sep 22 1966; typescript copy revised (Box 102)
      - On the Ministry, Episcopal Seminary of Southwest, Austin, Texas, May 22 1956; typescript copy revised (Box 102)
      - On need for ethical training of contemporary youth, Pittsburgh Pa., typescript copy revised (Box 102)
      - On Protestantism, Presbyterian Synod of N.Y., Oct 18 1950; typescript copy (Box 102)
      - On race relations, Interracial Leadership Conference, Apr 1957; printed material (Box 102)
      - On relationship of Christian faith to management problems, 1957; typescript copy (Box 102)
      - On religion and discipline, N.Y. Federation of Reform Synagogues, Dec 15 1957; typescript reproduction revised (Box 102)
      - On religion in education, Second Lecture, Adult Conference, Drew University, Madison, N.J., Jun 17 1952; typescript revised (Box 102)
      - On responsibilities of domestic relations lawyer American Bar Association, Family Section, Aug 25 1958; printed material (Box 102)
      - On role of professional clergy and lay person, Princeton Theological Seminary, Jun 5 1956; typescript (Box 102)
      - On Self-Acceptance and Self-Criticism, Third Lecture, Adult Conference, Drew University, Madison, N.J., Jun 18 1952; typescript revised (Box 102)
      - On the Sixties, Sep 21 1960; printed material (Box 102)
      - On the Synagogue, Chizuk Amuno Congregation, Baltimore, Md., typescript copy (Box 102)
      - On threats to freedom, Baccalaureate, Trinity College, Hartford, Conn., Jun 7 1953; printed material (Box 102)
      - On transcendence and freedom, Savings and Loan Association, San Francisco, California, Nov 20 1958; printed material (Box 102)
      - On U.N. and Middle East, Madison Square Garden, New York, Feb 25 1957; printed material (Box 102)
      - On vocation of lawyer, Trinity Church, New York, Oct 4 1956; typescript (Box 102)
      - On worship, 1957; typescript revised (Box 102)
      - On young people and the Church, typescript copy (Box 102)
      - Miscellaneous, notes for preparation of speeches (Box 102)
  - Miscellaneous
    This section contains assorted writings such as letters to editor, statements or testimony, before committees, miscellaneous material pertaining to specific publications for which Pike wrote frequently, and so on.
    - On abortion laws, letter to editor, Commonweal, 1966; incomplete, typescript copy (Box 102)
    - On Adolf Eichmann, San Francisco Examiner, Mar 30 1961; typescript copy revised (Box 102)
    - On America and Christianity and Crisis Articles, Newsweek, Aug 4 1962; draft A, typescript. rev.; draft B, typescript (Box 102)
    - On the American heritage in Church and state, Jan 1957; typescript copy revised (Box 102)
    - On Anglicans and Roman Catholics, letter to editor, Mamaroneck Daily Times, typescript copy (Box 102)
    - On Arizona Clergy and Incident in Rhodesia, Reveille, Feb 1966; typescript copy and typescript reproduction (Box 102)
    - On article by Habiby in The Living Church, typescript copy revised (Box 102)
    - On being a teen-ager, Teen, Feb 10 1969; typescript reproduction (Box 102)
    - On Billy Graham, New York Crusade, typescript copy (Box 102)
    - On Bishop Myer's sermon regarding Pope, Jun 6 1967; typescript revised (Box 102)
    - On Blake-Pike Proposal and Episcopal Church, typescript revised (Box 102)
    - On capital punishment, Mar 9 1960; typescript reproduction (Box 102)
    - On Cathedral Choir School, Feb 1954; printed material (Box 102)
    - On Christ, Newsweek, typescript copy (Box 102)
    - On Christian day-school education, typescript revised (Box 102)
    - On the Church and race, "That We May Be Whole" Intergroup Relations Committee, Diocese of California, 1961[?]; printed material (Box 102)
    - On church-state relations, Senate Judiciary Committee, Aug 2 1962; typescript reproduction (Box 102)
    - On comments of Dr. Glenn Archer of POAU, Dec 1953[?]; typescript revised (Box 102)
    - On communism, for use in case against Manchester Union, 1957; typescript copy (Box 102)
    - On computer dating, typescript (Box 102)
    - On conscience, This Week, Dec 1957; typescript copy revised (Box 102)
    - On Council for Middle Eastern Affairs, Feb 1957; typescript (Box 102)
    - On death of God, Playboy, typescript revised (Box 102)
    - On demonstrations against HUAC, May 13 1960; typescript reproduction (Box 102)
    - On demonstrations against racial justice in San Francisco, Apr 13 1964; printed material (Box 102)
    - On desegregation of San Francisco schools, 1962; printed material (Box 102)
    - On discrimination in inter-state travel facilities, May 27 1961; typescript (Box 102)
    - On Dr. Conant's charges of Church influence in education, 1952; draft A, typescript revised, draft B, typescript copy, typescript reproduction (Box 102)
    - "Doing the truth", notes, photocopied pages with corrections, correspondence, misc material (Box 102)
    - "Doctrine, Data and Due Process" for Bayne Comm., 1967; draft A, typescript reproduction rev.; draft B, typescript reproduction; fragments, typescript, typescript reproduction; 3 folders (Box 102)
    - On election as bishop, Sacramento Missionary, 1958; typescript copy (Box 102)
    - The Episcopalian, drafts, clippings, notes, correspondence, etc. for articles, interviews, excerpts, etc. published therein (Box 102)
    - On Episcopalians for the Faith, Apr 1961; typescript copy (Box 103)
    - On freedom behind Iron Curtain, Radio Liberation, Jul 18 1955; typescript revised, published material (Box 103)
    - "From 'Is' to 'Ought' to 'Is'," Yale Law School [?], typescript revised (Box 103)
    - On going steady, Life, 1957; typescript copy (Box 103)
    - On greatest problem in 1970's, Esquire, Aug 1969; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript copy (Box 103)
    - Herder and Herder, 1968-1969; drafts, clippings, notes, correspondence, etc. for articles, interviews, excerpts, etc. published therein (Box 103)
    - If This Be Heresy, new epilog (Box 103)
    - On last sermon as bishop, letter to editor, Newsweek, 1966; typescript copy revised (Box 103)
    - On legal counseling, typescript copy (Box 103)
    - On Lent, Feb 23 1962; typescript copy (Box 103)
    - "Man's Salvation: A Comparison of Roman and Protestant Doctrine", 1944; typescript copy (Box 103)
    - On marriage, Love and Marriage Clinic, U.S.S. Hancock, 1966; printed material (Box 103)
    - On Margaret Mead's article, "Marriage In Two Steps" Redbook Magazine, Sep 1966; typescript copy (Box 103)
    - On Martin Buber, 1967; typescript reproduction (Box 103)
    - On the McCollum decision, letter to editor, Church-State Newsletter, typescript copy (Box 103)
    - On medical profession, letter to editor, San Francisco Chronicle, 1961; typescript copy (Box 103)
    - On minorities and law enforcement in California, Jan 18 1963; typescript reproduction (Box 103)
    - On Morningside Heights institutions, 1958; typescript copy (Box 103)
    - On most quoted phrase in Bible, typescript copy (Box 103)
    - National Catholic Reporter, drafts, clippings, notes, correspondence, etc. for articles, interviews, excerpts, etc. published therein (Box 103)
    - On National Hemophilia Foundation, Feb 1957; typescript copy (Box 103)
    - On Olav Hammarstrom's designs, typescript reproduction (Box 103)
    - The Other Gospel, correspondence, notes, legal agreements, etc. relating to motion picture adaptation; 2 folders (Box 103)
    - Outline of some differences in Roman Catholic practices and Protestant and early church practices, typescript (Box 103)
    - On Park in Marin County, May 18 1962; typescript copy (Box 103)
    - Playboy, drafts, clippings, notes, correspondence, etc. for articles, interviews, excerpts, etc. published therein (Box 103)
    - On population control, Dec 29 1962; draft A, typescript revised; draft B, typescript reproduction, (Box 103)
    - Prayers, 1956-1966; typescript and typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On program of Cathedral of St. John the Divine, Mar 1957; typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On prospects for 1964, San Francisco Examiner, Dec 1963; typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On psychic phenomena, Jubilee, Feb 1968; typescript reproduction (Box 104)
    - "RX For Apologetics", 1944; typescript (Box 104)
    - Reader's Digest, 1961; letter to editor, typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On relation of changes in church thinking to changes in church architecture, Jan 3 1968; typescript revised (Box 104)
    - On relationship of Church and State, as proposed by Ottaviani and Murray, incomplete, typescript (Box 104)
    - On religious broadcasting, New York Daily News, typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On report of Bayne Commission, Aug 12 1967; typescript (Box 104)
    - On St. James the Fisherman, Wellfleet, Mass., 1957; typescript copy (Box 104)
    - San Francisco Examiner, Sep 11 1962; letter to editor, typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On saving, The Living Church, typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On Sharkey-Brown-Isaacs Bill to eliminate segregation in housing, Dec 19 1957 (Box 104)
    - On "show business," Pageant, Jan 1957; typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On Sister Mary Aloysius, one of Pike's teachers, 1968 (Box 104)
    - On spending a billion dollars, Encyclopedia Yearbook, Nov 1959; typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On Supreme Court prayer decision, Jun 25, 1962; Jun 17 1963; typescript copy and typescript reproduction; 2 folders (Box 104)
    - On tenth anniversary of Israel, 1958; typescript copy (Box 104)
    - "Underground gospels", correspondence, notes, clippings, etc. on various non-traditional gospels and interpretations, including correspondence with author John Allegro (Box 104)
    - On USO, Jan 23 1962; typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On various movies, including Baby Doll, 1956; 1958; typescript copy (Box 104)
    - On Vatican II, Esprit, Aug 1961 (?); typescript (Box 104)
    - On voting on Sunday, Family Weekly, published material (Box 104)
    - Women in ministry, subject file, includes notes, clippings, photocopies of writings by Pike and others (Box 104)
    - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 105)
    - Miscellaneous magazines (Time, Rampart, etc.) -, drafts, clippings, notes, correspondence, etc. for articles, interviews, excerpts, etc. published therein (Box 105)
- Writings by others
  - Allen, Roland, "The Case for Voluntary Clergy", 1923; printed material (Box 105)
  - American Bar Association, on Chief Justice Gibson, by Aquinas Social Studies Inc. for the ABA (Box 105)
  - American Friends of the Middle East, 4th Annual Report, 1954-1955; printed material (Box 105)
  - Bailey, William L., miscellaneous religious material, 1966; typescript annotated (Box 105)
  - Banowsky, William and Mount, Anson, "Christianity and Hedonism: A Clash of Philosophies", printed material (Box 105)
  - Berman, Harold J., "Law and Love", Nov 4 1963; printed material (Box 105)
  - Bishop of Derby, "The Plan of Church Union in North India and Pakistan and the Scheme for Church Union in Ceylon", 1958(?); printed material (Box 105)
  - Blake, Eugene Carson "A Proposal Toward the Reunion of Christ's Church", 1960; published material (Box 105)
  - Blake, Eugene Carson "Second Thoughts on Church Union", 1965; printed material (Box 105)
  - Bowden, Gerald, "Rights of Faith vs. Rights of the Faithful", 1966; typescript (Box 105)
  - Braden, Don, "The Agony of the Southern Minister", 1967; typescript (Box 105)
  - Brother, Martin, "The Melish Controversy", typescript (Box 105)
  - Brown, Robert R., "Bigger than Little Rock", 1958; published material (Box 105)
  - Bruening, Thomas M., "The Motivation of Ghetto Residents Toward Manpower Development Programs", 1967(?); typescript copy (Box 105)
  - Burnette, William A. "Death of Good Dialogue", typescript carbon (Box 105)
  - Burnette, William A. and Mason, Martha, "How Jesus Became the Messiah", typescript (Box 105)
  - Carter, Harvey L., "Zebulon Montgomery Pike--Pathfinder and Patriot", 1956; published material (Box 105)
  - Church Information Board, "Deaconesses in the Church of England", 1950; published material (Box 105)
  - Church of England (unknown committee), "The Family in Contemporary Society", 1958(?); uncorrected proof, printed material (Box 105)
  - Church of England, "The Lambeth Conference" The Encyclical Letter from the Bishops together with the Resolutions and Reports, 1958; published material (Box 105)
  - Church of South India, "An Order for the Lord's Supper", 1957; published material (Box 105)
  - Comstock, W. Richard, "Theology After the 'Death of God'" Cross Currents, 1966; published material (Box 106)
  - Crenshaw, Robert E., comments by theologians on Crenshaw's cosmological theories, 1968; typescript copy (Box 106)
  - Davidson, Neville, "The Vocation of the Church", 1962; published material (Box 106)
  - Davis, Jerome, Adventuring For Justice, Freedom and Peace, 1967; typescript copy annotated (Box 106)
  - Doan, Gilbert, "Believer's World", 1968; signed and inscribed to Pike (Box 106)
  - Duddington, John W., "The Historic Jesus", 1961; published material (Box 106)
  - Dunmire, Walter, "The Blue Side of A Lonesome Seed", typescript (Box 106)
  - Eakin, Thomas, "The Doctrine of the Trinity", 1943; printed material (Box 106)
  - Engelhardt, Hanns, "The Lawyer's Contribution to the Progress of Christian Unity" Ecumenical, 1969; printed material (Box 106)
  - Ferre, Nels F.S., "The Fabric of Paul Tillich's Theology", 1968; published material (Box 106)
  - Ferre, Nels F.S., "Tillich and the Nature of Transcendence", 1968; published material (Box 106)